<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before his Maiesty at Windsore, the 19. of Iuly. 1625. By Henrie Leslie, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary</title>
            <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108502</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844160</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8949</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05342)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8949)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 805:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before his Maiesty at Windsore, the 19. of Iuly. 1625. By Henrie Leslie, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] L[itchfield] and W[illiam] T[urner] for William Turner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before his Maiestie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8949:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8949:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE HIS MAIESTY at <hi>Windſore,</hi> the 19. of <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1625.</p>
            <p>By HENRIE LESLIE, one of his MAIESTIES Chaplaines in Ordinary.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>V. 28.14.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his heart ſhall fall into Euill.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IER. 45.4.</hi>
               </bibl> Thus ſaith the Lord, Behold, that which I haue built, will I breake downe, and that which I haue planted, will I plucke vp, euen this whole land, and ſeekeſt thou great things for thy ſelfe?</q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by I. L. and W. T. for WILLIAM TVRNER. Anno Dom. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8949:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8949:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE IAMES.</head>
            <p>EARLE OF CARLILE, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> OF DONCASTER, BARON OF SALEY, one of his Majeſties moſt honorable Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, &amp; Knight of the moſt <hi>Noble Order of the Garter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, and my ſingular good Lord, when I preached this Sermon, I applyed my ſelfe to this time of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſtudying more to
<pb facs="tcp:8949:3"/>profite, then pleaſe: yet it did receiue a greater approbation from all, than any thing could deſerue that proceeded from my weakeneſſe. And your Honour was pleaſed to demaund a Copie of it, which I here humbly preſent vnto You, in a poore and plaine ſtile as it was preached, beſeeching your Lordſhip to take in good part this ſmall offering, from him who ſhall alwayes pray for Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours proſperitie in this life, and happines hereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours in all dutie</hi> Henrie Leſlie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:8949:3"/>
            <head>A Table of the Contents.</head>
            <p>The Text diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<list>
                  <item>1 the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart,</hi> which ſignifies
<list>
                        <item>1 The dryneſſe of the Soule.</item>
                        <item>2 The ſtiffeneſſe of the VVill.</item>
                        <item>3 the ſenſleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of
<list>
                              <item>1 the mind
<list>
                                    <item>1 Not vnderſtanding the word.</item>
                                    <item>2 Vnderſtanding the word, but not being moued thereby.</item>
                                    <item>3 Being moued, but not effectually.</item>
                                    <item>4 Being prouoked to doe the contrary.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being
<list>
                                    <item>1 The broad conſcience.</item>
                                    <item>2 The ſleeping conſcience.</item>
                                    <item>3 The ſlumbring conſcience.</item>
                                    <item>4 The benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med conſcience.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>3 of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which is
<list>
                                    <item>1 Carnall ſecuritie.</item>
                                    <item>2 Senſeleſſe indolencie.</item>
                                    <item>3 Worldly ſorrow.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 the cauſe of this euil diuers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuerſe hardening,
<list>
                        <item>1 Naturall, from our firſt Parents.</item>
                        <item>2 Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary, from God, harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<list>
                              <item>1 Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely
<list>
                                    <item>1 Forſaking them.</item>
                                    <item>2 Permitting them.</item>
                                    <item>3 Not puniſhing them.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely
<list>
                                    <item>1 By outward obiects.</item>
                                    <item>2 By themſelues.</item>
                                    <item>3 By Satan.</item>
                                    <item>4 By his inviſible power.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 Voluntary, from our ſelues, men hardening their hearts by a cuſtome of ſinne.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The Remedies againſt this Euill, which are ſet downe, <hi>Eight</hi> in number.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8949:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8949:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE HIS MAIESTY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 3.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Harden not your hearts.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Apoſtle was inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Holy Ghoſt:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.40.</note> yet here that his words might haue the more authoritie, he alleageth the ſaying of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Wherefore as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if ye will heare his voice, harden not your hearts.</hi> This ſaying of the Holy Ghoſt is by the mouth of <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 95.7. So that the author of this exhortation makes it fit for this place, it being the meditation of a King, the, repetition of it makes it fit for this time,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8949:5"/>time: for was ſuch a caveat needfull not only in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> time, but alſo afterwards in the Apoſtle's time? &amp; is it not much more neceſſary at this time, when God by his judgments doth call vs to <hi>weeping and to mourning,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 22.12.</note> and to baldneſſe, and to girding with ſackcloth.</hi> Giue me leaue therefore to redouble this exhortation vnto you, <hi>Harden not your hearts.</hi> Wherein we may conſider theſe three particulars, 1 The euill to be auoided, and that is <hi>hardneſſe of heart.</hi> 2. The cauſe of this euill, which my text ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to aſcribe vnto our ſelues, ſaying, <hi>Harden not your hearts.</hi> 3 The remedies to be vſed againſt this euill, that our hearts may not be hardened. The firſt will ſerue for conviction, the ſecond for informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the third for direction.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, the euill to be auoided is called <hi>hardneſſe of hearts.</hi> And what this is, is not eaſie to be vnderſtood. For beſides that the phraſe is meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoricall, this euill is of that nature, that it taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſenſe and knowledge of ſinne. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. it is ſaid of the Gentiles, their <hi>vnderstanding was darkened,</hi> and why? <hi>becauſe of the hardneſſe of their hearts.</hi> So that this point of hardening is not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, becauſe our owne hearts are hardened. But if we take and weigh it in the ballance of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, there we ſhall finde many equivalent phraſes, which will helpe vs to finde out the nature, and the weight of this euill. In Scripture it is called the <hi>bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen brow, Iſa.</hi> 48.4. <hi>The iron ſinew,</hi> ibid. <hi>the ſpirit of perverſeneſſe, Iſa.</hi> 19.14. <hi>The ſpirit of ſlumber,</hi> or <hi>the Spirit of compunction.</hi> Iſa. 29.10. <hi>The Wine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8949:5"/>of giddines,</hi> Pſal. 60.3. <hi>Spirituall drunkenneſſe.</hi> Iſa. 29.9. <hi>the ſeared Conſcience,</hi> 1. Tim. 4.2. <hi>the hard necke,</hi> 2 King. 17.14. <hi>the ſtiffenecke.</hi> Deut. 31.27. <hi>the vncircumciſed heart and eare.</hi> Act. 7.58. <hi>the face harder then a ſtone.</hi> Ier. 5.3. the <hi>fatte and groſſe heart,</hi> Iſa. 6.10. <hi>blinded eyes.</hi> Ioh. 12.40. <hi>Dull</hi> or <hi>heauy</hi> eares. Iſa. 6.20. <hi>The reprobate mind.</hi> Rom. 1.28. <hi>The ſtonie heart.</hi> Ezech. 11.19. <hi>The heart of Adamant.</hi> Zach. 7.12. and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <hi>ſtubborneſſe of heart.</hi> Ier. 13.10. Now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare we hardnes of heart with theſe the like phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and we ſhall find that a hard heart, is nothing elſe, but a ſoule that is confirmed in ſinfull cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>But that we may better vnderſtand the ſeuerall kinds and degrees hereof, let vs examine from whence this ſpeach is borrowed. The heart when it is ſaid to be hard, is taken ſometimes for the whole ſoule, ſometimes for the mind, ſometimes for the will, ſometimes for the conſcience, &amp; other whiles for the affections, according to the ſeuerall acceptions of the <hi>word hardnes,</hi> which is the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity aſcribed to the heart, and that, not properly, but metaphorically. The metaphore is taken ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from a ſtone, as the Scripture ſeemes to imply, calling our <hi>hearts</hi> not only hard, but alſo ſtonie; for the hardnes of a <hi>ſtone</hi> is accompanied with great <hi>dryneſſe,</hi> alſo the <hi>hardneſſe</hi> of it, makes it ſtiffe and inflexible, not apt to bow or bend. In all which it greatly reſembleth the corruption of the heart. Or els the Metaphore is from that <hi>Callum</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8949:6"/>or hard thicke skin which couereth the hand of the labourer, and the heele of the traveller: For as that is void of all ſenſe and feeling, ſo is the heart in this ſtate of corruption. And that this is the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion may appeare by <hi>the Phraſe</hi> muſt commonly vſed in the New <hi>Teſtament, to ſignifie hardneſſe of heart.</hi> It is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The word</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth the thicke skin that couereth the palmes of the hands, and the feete, or the <hi>hardnes</hi> that is in the ioynts, and the ſmall bones that are the inſtruments of motion, making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>ſtiffe,</hi> ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and benummed. Hence thoſe members that are thus obdured, are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. but it matters not, whence the Metaphore is taken; for certainly it is from things corporall, whereof onely <hi>hardneſſe</hi> is an affection. And whereſoeuer it is, it hath theſe three properties. 1. <hi>Dryneſſe, that which is hard is dry,</hi> not hauing any moiſture to ſoften it. 2. <hi>Stiffeneſſe,</hi> and inflexibleneſſe; for ſaith the Philoſopher,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt.</hi> L. 4. <hi>Mereor.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Durum eſt, quod non cedit in ſeipſum ſecundum ſuperficiem.</hi> That is hard which cannot yeeld, bow, or bend into any other forme, then what it hath. 3. Vnmoueableneſſe &amp; <hi>Senſeleſneſſe,</hi> that which neither can be bruiſed and broken with ſtrokes, nor pierced with ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is hard. Now when <hi>hardneſſe</hi> is aſcribed to the <hi>heart,</hi> it is to ſignify either one or all of <hi>theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt hardneſſe of heart imports the <hi>dryneſſe</hi> of the Soule; for it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, here vſed, which ſignifieth properlie to dry vp and wither. For as in naturall things, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8949:6"/>in the Soule, there is a watering which is good and comfortable, and there is a drying vp which is dangerous and hurtfull. The watering is with the dew of grace:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note> for God in Scripture compares his <hi>grace</hi> vnto things <hi>liquid,</hi> as Oile, Wine, Milke, &amp; cheifly Water. There is a well of liuing waters for the Soule. Ioh. 4.14, It is called a riuer of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters. Ioh. 7.38. The preaching of grace is called watering 1. Cor. 3.6. For as water ſerues to ſupple and ſoften that which is dry and withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; ſo doth <hi>Gods grace</hi> ſoften and ſupple our wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Soules. And of all kindes of water it is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>likened</hi> to raine and dew; for that is moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to water the earth. Deut. 32.2. <hi>My do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſhall drop as the raine, and my ſpeach ſhall ſtill as the dew.</hi> Thus when God promiſeth his grace vnto his people, he ſaith, that he will come vnto them <hi>as the raine, as the latter and former raine vnto the earth.</hi> Hoſ. 6.3. Which ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude giues vs to vnderſtand, that our ſoules are as a dry and thirſtie ground, burnt vp with the heat of the ſun, and ſo barren and fruitleſſe, and Gods grace as the raine that waters the earth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it fruitfull. The like promiſe is Iſa. 44.3. <hi>I will powre water vpon the thirſtie, and flouds vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the dry ground.</hi> Which is according to that chap. 35.6. <hi>In the Wildernes ſhall waters breake out, and ſtreames in the Deſert.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Mag.</note> Now where this watering is not, there muſt be withering, <hi>Si Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue irrigatio defuerit omnis plantatio exareſcit.</hi> That plant which is not watered with the dew of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8949:7"/>grace will wither at the roote, and neuer grow vp in the courts of the Lord. Therefore it is ſaid, that the godly <hi>are like the tree planted by the waters ſide;</hi> Pſal. 1.3. There is watering: but the wicked, <hi>as an Oake whoſe leafe fadeth; and as a garden that hath no water.</hi> Iſa. 1.30. There is withering and <hi>drieneſſe.</hi> Yea, beſides the want of the Iuyce of grace, which cauſeth dryneſſe, our ſoules are alſo burnt vp with the heat of concupiſcence, and ſo naturally exceeding dry and withered, barren and fruitles.
<note place="margin">Ezech 11.19. &amp; 36.26.</note> And therfore they are not only called bard, but alſo ſtonie. A <hi>ſtone</hi> of all hard things is the dryeſt, no Iuyce not Liquor can be drawen out of it. Mettalls albeit very hard may more caſily be diſtilled, and therefore it was a great miracle, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the rocke, waters did flow in the deſert. So in our hearts there is no Iuyce of grace, no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be drawne out of them, but by an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie worke of Gods power.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hardneſſe of heart ſignifieth the ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and inflexibleneſſe of the will; ſo that a hard heart is a diſobedient and vnyeelding heart, ſuch as indeed our hearts are by nature, peruerſe &amp; fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſtubborne, obſtinate, and rebellious, not ſo much as flexible vnto holy obedience; but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther averſe vnto that which is good, and prone to deſire that alone which is euill: So that if God doe will our conuerſion,
<note place="margin">Math. 23.37.</note> we doe nill it; if he would gather vs vnder his wings, we will not be gathered. If he command vs that which is iuſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.11.</note> we <hi>refuſe to hearken, and pull away the ſhoulder. If he ſend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8949:7"/>vs all his ſernants the Prophets,
<note place="margin">Ier. 33.15.15.</note> exhorting vs to returne euery man from his euill way, and amend our workes; yet we will not incline our eare nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey.</hi> Yea although the Lord denounce his indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and threaten a plague, except we returne;
<note place="margin">Ier. 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22.</note> yet we will <hi>walke after our owne imaginations, and doe euery man after the ſubburneſſe of his wicked heart.</hi> Finally, though God <hi>ſtretchforth his hands all the day long;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 65.2.</note> yet we remaine <hi>a diſobedient and gainſaying people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 13.10.</note> This kind of hardneſſe is more properlie called, <hi>ſtubburnes of heart.</hi> And it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aptly, ſignified by the <hi>ſtiffe-neck, hard necke, and necke that is an iron ſinew.</hi> For ſinewes are the inſtruments of motion, and all the ſinewes goe downe from the head to the body by the necke, ſo that if either the necke ſhould be hard and ſtiffe; or if the ſinewes were of iron; it ſhould not be poſſible for the head to bow downe: ſo the heart that is in this eſtate of rebellion, cannot bow down, nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it ſelfe vnto the yoake of Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And that this is the meaning of <hi>theſe phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> may appeare by the words, rebellion, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, obſtinacie joyned with them, as a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Deut. 31.27. <hi>I know thy rebellion and thy ſtiffe-necke.</hi> 2. King. 17.24. <hi>they would not obey but hardened their neckes.</hi> Iſa. 48.4. <hi>becauſe I knew that thou art obſtinate, and thy necke as an iron ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 11. &amp; &amp; 36.26.</note> Finally I thinke God had a ſpeciall reſpect vnto this ſtiffenes of the will, calling our hearts ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. For iron is as hard as any ſtone; yet he calls it not <hi>Cor ferreum,</hi> but <hi>lapideum:</hi> becauſe iron,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8949:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>though very hard, yet is in ſome ſort flexible, the fire will molliſie it, and make it pliable into any forme: but ſo is not a ſtone, the fire it ſelfe cannot ſoften it, nor make it bend into any other forme, then what it hath. So is it with our hearts, they are no waies flexible into holy obedience, there is not ſo much as any inclination to good in them, So that the Lord in our conuerſion, muſt not onely giue vs a power to worke, but alſo, a will to deſire; for a man without grace is not onely vnable to chooſe, and doe that which is good; but alſo he cannot ſo much as affect it, or aſpire vnto it. He cannot co-operate with God working in him, nor open the doore to God <hi>knocking,</hi> nor hearken to God calling, nor yeeld vnto God drawing him. But God muſt firſt breath grace into his heart, and of vnwilling make him willing. For <hi>no man can come vnto me</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>except the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draw him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.44.</note> Where to <hi>ſignifie</hi> the mighty wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Gods power, overcomming all reſiſtance in the will of man, he calls our <hi>converſion a drawing.</hi> And this much he doth imply, when he ſaith, he will take away the ſtonie heart; not, I will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſtonie heart into a fleſhlie,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 36.26.</note> but <hi>I will take away the ſtonie heart, and giue you a heart of fleſh;</hi> ſignifying thereby, that there is nothing in our corrupt nature that hath affinitie with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, whereof we are made partakers in our regeneration: but that our whole old nature muſt be taken away, and a new giuen vs. A litle mending will not ſerue the turne, a new making is required.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8949:8"/>
            <p>Thirdly, hardneſſe of heart is vſed to expreſſe the vnmoueableneſſe and ſenſeleſſeneſſe of heart. So that a hard heart is a dead heart, which nothing can moue, neither word, nor Sacraments, miracles, nor motions of the ſpirit, neither ſenſe of ſinne, nor of Iudgement for ſinne.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 5. <hi>de Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Bernard</hi> deſcribeth a hard heart. <hi>Quid est cor durum? ipſum est quod nec com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punctione ſcinditur, nec pietate mollitur, nec move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur preeibus; minis non cedit, flagellis duratur, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratum est ad beneficia, impavidum ad pericula, &amp;c.</hi> This kind of hardnes according to the difference of the obiect and ſubiect, is threefold: 1. a deadneſſe of the minde, when we are not moued with the meanes of ſaluation, which God hath appointed to ſoften our hearts. 2. a deadneſſe of conſcience, when we are not moued with our owne ſinnes. 3. a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the affections, when we are not moued with God's judgements.</p>
            <p>The firſt which is a deadneſſe or dulneſſe of the mind, is a high degree of hardneſſe; when the ſoule is not onely dry and deſtitute of grace, and alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible and vnwilling to receiue grace: but further it cannot ſo much as be moued with theſe meanes God hath appointed to beget grace. <hi>God's word is ſharper then a two edged ſword, Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>It is like a hammer that breaketh the ſtones, Ier.</hi> 23.29. and in that ſame place it is reſembled to fire able to melt the hardeſt mettals.
<note place="margin">Deut. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Finally it is compared to dew and raine that watereth &amp; ſo mollifieth the ground. And yet this Word, this mighty Word, cannot pierce, it cannot bruiſe, it cannot melt, it cannot
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8949:9"/>moiſten our hard and ſtonie, our dry and withered hearts:
<note place="margin">Iob. 41.24. Iſa. 48.4.</note> for as it is ſaid of Leviathan, our heart is harder than the <hi>nether milstone.</hi> To ſignifie this, it is called, <hi>the braſen browe.</hi> Ye know a man's for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is moſt obvious to ſtroakes; but if the ſame were of ſo hard a mettall as braſſe, it could not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be broken or peirced. But ſuch is the corrupt heart of man: though God's Word be like a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer that breaketh the rockes in pieces, and ſharper then any two edged ſword; yet no threatnings &amp; admonitions of God's Word can breake it, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and intreaties can pierce it. Yea though this Word be ſealed with Sacraments, confirmed with miracles, &amp; accompanied with the inward motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſpirit: yet all theſe are but as an arrow ſhot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a braſen wall,
<note place="margin">Iob. 41.29.</note> our heart being as the ſcales of Leviathan,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.10.</note> who laughes at the ſhaking of the ſpeare. This is alſo well ſignified by <hi>the fat heart;</hi> for as the heart being couered with a maſſe of fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cannot ſeele any thing; no more can the mind in this eſtate of obduration; for as the Poe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaith,
<q>Triplex circa praecordia ferrum.</q> This is likewiſe vnderſtood by the <hi>blinded eyes</hi> that cannot ſee,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.10. Act. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>the dull or heauie eares</hi> that cannot <hi>heare,</hi> and the <hi>vncircumciſed heart and eare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This dulnes, in not being moued with the word, Saeraments, &amp;c. hath foure degrees. 1. when a man doth not ſo much as conceiue what is ſaid, hauing his cognitations darkened, &amp; his eyes couered with the ſcales of ignorance: or if he doe conceiue it, yet he doth not attentiuely conſider it. This is ſignified
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8949:9"/>in the Parable, by the ſeed that fell by the highwaies ſide, as Chriſt expounds it, <hi>Whenſoeuer a man hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the word of the kingdome, and vnderſtandeth it not: the euill one commeth and catcheth away that which was ſowen in his heart:
<note place="margin">Matth. 13.19.</note> this is hee who hath receiued the ſeede by the wayes ſide.</hi> The diſciples themſelues were charged with this dulneſſe, Mar. 6.52. <hi>They couſidered not the miracle of the loaues,</hi> (that is, they did not ſee Gods power in that worke) <hi>for their heart was hardened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond degree of this dulneſſe is when a man, though in ſome meaſure he vnderſtand what is ſaid, yet he is not moued thereby. God's Word is a hammer: this hammer with tenne miracles, gaue tenne mighty ſtroakes at <hi>Pharao</hi> his heart, and yet could not breake it. So it was with <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> he heard the commandement of God againſt the altar he had ſet vp, he ſaw the altar cleaue aſunder, and the aſhes fall out from it, according to the ſigne gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the Prophet: his hand which he put forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prophet was dryed vp, and after healed by the prayer of the Prophet: yet was not he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at all this. When the Prophet cryed to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, <hi>O Altar, Altar, thus ſaith the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the altar heard and claue aſunder: but <hi>Ieroboam's</hi> heart was harder then the altar; for he heard the Word, and his heart did not breake.
<note place="margin">Act. 7.50.</note> Thus it was with the Iewes, being <hi>ſtiffe-necked, they did alwayes reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> namely in the miniſtrie of the Word.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> degree of this dulneſſe and oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Word, is when one is moued thereby,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8949:10"/>but not effectually, euen moued in affection, but his will is not changed, nor heart ſoftened. This happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth diuers wayes: for the word ſtirreth vp ſundrie affections euen in wicked and hard-hearted men, as aſtoniſhment, feare, joy. Sometimes it worketh only aſtoniſhment, &amp; wondring, their hearts being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, hearing the Word, that it hath more then humane force. This is that effect which many felt hearing Chriſt, when they were aſtonied at his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<note place="margin">Marc. 1.22. Ioh. 7.46. Habac. 1.5.</note> as teaching with authority, ſaying. <hi>What manner of doctrine is this? neuer man ſpake like this man.</hi> Thus the wicked <hi>wonder</hi> and <hi>vaniſh.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Word preached bringeth not only won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but feare alſo; not only filleth the eares with ſound, and the heart with aſtoniſhment; but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer ſhaketh and terrifieth the conſcience. This ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect did befall <hi>Felix;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act, 24.26.</note> for hearing <hi>Paul</hi> he trembled; and ſometimes it goeth further, not only rauiſhing with admiration, and ſtriking the conſcience with terrour; but alſo delighting the heart with ſome joy for a time. This effect was in <hi>Herod,</hi> who heard <hi>Iohn</hi> gladly.
<note place="margin">Mare, 6.20.</note> And it is in temporarie beleeuers, well ſignified by the ſeed ſowen in ſtonie ground, as Chriſt expounds it, Math. 13.20. therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith of theſe temporaries,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.</note> that they <hi>taſted of the heauenly gift,</hi> that is, they were affected with ſome taſte of God's goodnes manifeſted in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. But it was onely a ſmall taſte, they neuer dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted it, nor concocted it by the vitall hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of God's ſpirit; farre leſſe were they filled with that ſweet peace and joy which the ſpirit of adoption work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the faithfull.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:8949:10"/>
            <p>The laſt degree is when a man is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moued effectually by the word, that he is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouoked to doe the contrarie:
<note place="margin">Origen.</note> for ſuch is the corruption of mans nature, <hi>vt ea quae prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur magis deſiderantur.</hi> Our corrupt nature is like a reſtie horſe, who the more he is ſpurred forward, the more he goeth backward; and like a ſtreame, whch being dammed vp, rageth, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and ouerfloweth all the bankes. therefore is the commandement ſaid to be an occaſion of ſin, and Chriſt is called a rocke of offence, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles a ſauour of death. Take an example here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> he is commanded to let the people goe, and the more he is vrged, the ſtiffer and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borner he is, and the <hi>more he rebelleth</hi> againſt God. And the ſame may be ſaid of the Iewes: God foretelleth what ſhould bee the euent of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaias</hi> miniſtrie, namely, that he ſhould make their hearts fat, and their eares heauy, and ſhut their eyes. So that even the word becommeth vnto them the meanes of hardning. As the middle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the aire is more cold by the <hi>Antiperiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> ſo the heart of a reprobate is more hard by the word, though the word in it ſelfe bee full of vitall heart for to ſoften the heart. As the hammer though it breakes the rockes yet the ſmithes ſtithie, the more the hammer ſtrikes vpon it the harder it is; and as the heate of the ſunne though it melt waxe, yet it dryeth the clay: and as the raine, though it mollifie the earth, yet hardens ſand: ſo the word breaketh, melteth and mollifieth the hearts of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8949:11"/>Godlie: and yet obdurates, dryes and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens the wicked, but accidentallie, the fault being in their owne diſpoſition.
<note place="margin">Itpleaſed ſome to cenſure me, that I did ill to alleadge the ſpirit of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction,</hi> as a phraſe equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto it. Therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that I tooke not <hi>Compunction</hi> paſſiuely for contrition, as when they are ſaid to be <hi>compuncti corde, Act.</hi> 2.37. but actiuely, for a fretting againſt the word. And ſo the Scripture takes it; For <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.8. that which is viually rendred, the ſpirit of <hi>ſlumber</hi> is not vnfitly by others tranſlated the <hi>Spirit of Compunction.</hi> And I appeale from their learning, to the common ſenſe of the meaneſt Reader, whether in that place it be contrary to hardneſſe of heart, or all one with it: for hauing ſaid, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> were hardned, for confirmation thereof, hee alleadgeth this, as <hi>it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, God hath giuen them the Spirit of Compunction;</hi> and after addes, <hi>Eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and eares that they ſhould not beare:</hi> loyning in one, two places the of propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
               </note> This in Scripture is called the ſpirit of <hi>compunction,</hi> which implyeth a kind of fretting, chaffing, and violent ſtirring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the word: as in thoſe that braſt for anger at the Apoſtles Act. 5.33. That gnaſhed with their teeth at <hi>Stephen.</hi> Act. 7.54.</p>
            <p>The ſecond kind of this ſenſeleſneſſe is in the conſcience, and <hi>reſpecteth</hi> the ſinnes which a man committeth, when a man is not touched with ſenſe and ſorrow for the ſame.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.2. Iſa. 29.9. Pſal. 60.3. Iſa. 29.10.</note> This is the <hi>ſeared conſcience, ſpirituall drunkenneſſe, the wine of giddineſſe or drowſineſſe, the ſpirit of ſlumber</hi> or <hi>deade ſleepe.</hi> for when any part of the body is ſeared with a hot iron, it looſeth all ſence, life and motion, alſo when a man is drunken, he knowes not, he careth not what he doth. And finallie thoſe who are ouercome with drowſineſſe or ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering, cannot eaſilie with ſtirring or pricking be awaked. So he that is come to this height of hardneſſe, is without all ſenſe of ſinne, he neither knoweth nor careth what euill he doth; and hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8949:11"/>
               <hi>is neuer moued</hi> with any ſtirring or pricking of his conſcience. Of ſuch the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> they are <hi>Past feeling,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>This ſeared conſcience hath ſeuerall degrees. There is the broade conſcience, when a man is not moued with any ſinne except it be very heynous. There is the ſleeping conſcience, when a man is not touched with the ſenſe of any ſinne, be it neuer ſo greivous, for a long time;
<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> yet at laſt <hi>tranquillitas ista tenpeſtas eſt,</hi> this calme proues a ſtorrne; and he is awakened, either by the preaching of the law, or the terrors of death, or ſome greivous calamitie. and there is the ſlumbering conſcience, which hath ſome ſenſe of ſinne, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had,
<note place="margin">Exod. 9.27.</note> when hee cryed out, <hi>I haue ſinned:</hi> but neuer any ſound ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it: he feeles not with <hi>Iob,</hi> the terrors of God fighting againſt him, and the inuenomed arrowes of the almightie ſticking faſt in his ribs. This is but like the ſweating of a ſtone in moiſt weather, which notwithſtanding retaines its naturall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dryneſſe. finallie their is the benummed conſciene, when a man hath neither ſenſe of ſinne, nor ſorrow for it, but is like a man in a phrenſie, or one fallen into a pleaſant ſleepe, who though he be exceeding ſick yet he feeles no paine and as in ſome kind of ſickneſſe a man may die laughing: ſo where this degree of hardneſſe is, a man may deſcend into the pit of hell trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing and reioycing. Whereof I will onely ſay with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin, quid miſerius miſero non miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante ſeipſum.</hi> None are ſo deſperately ſick as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8949:12"/>they who feele not their diſeaſe. when the pulſe doth not beat, the bodie is in a moſt dangerous eſtate: that ſchoole will ſoone decay where the monitor doth not complaine: that army muſt neceſſarily be ſurpriſed where watches &amp; alarums be not kept: that towne is diſſolute where no clockes are vſed. But the conſcience is to the ſoule, as the pulſe to the body, the monitor to the ſchoole, the watch to the armie, the clocke to a towne. And therefore when it is ſilent, the ſoule is in a moſt deſperate caſe.</p>
            <p>The third kinde of this ſenſeleſneſſe is in the affections and reſpecteth Gods Iudgements vpon vs for ſinne, when theſe cannot worke vpon a ſoule any good effect, but are as it were loſt labour, as God accounteth them <hi>Iſa</hi> 1.5. <hi>Why ſhould yee he ſtricken any more? yee will revoult more and more.</hi> Indeede affliction is the moſt effectuall meanes, for to make our heart relent and reſolue into the teares of vnfained repentance, either the croſſe will doe it or nothing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moral. l.</hi> 26. <hi>c.</hi> 23.</note> as <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith, <hi>aurem cordis tribulatio aperit quam ſaepe huius mundi proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas claudit,</hi> which is the ſame with that of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu,
<note place="margin">Iob 33.16.</note> God openeth the eares of men by their correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he had ſealed, that he might cauſe man to turne away from his purpoſe.</hi> Therefore we find that afflictions are the laſt meanes which God ordinarily vſeth to convert obſtinate ſinners. When neither the oile of his gracious bountie will ſoftenour ſtony hearts; nor his Word which is the ſword of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, pierce them; when neither the ſweet ſound of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8949:12"/>his gracious promiſes will allure vs to obedience nor the terrible thunder of his fearefull threatnings reſtraine vs from ſinne. In the laſt place he viſits our iniquities with the rod, &amp; our ſinnes with ſcourges, knowing that if our caſe be not deſperate, we will at leaſt be reclaimed by his judgments. Thus the Lord hauing complained much of the rebellion of his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. in end he promiſeth them mercie, and ſheweth how he would reforme them, euen by caſting them into the fierie ſurnace of affliction, thereby to purifie them, and conſume away the droſſe of their ſinnes, that they might ſhine againe in their wonted beautie:
<note place="margin">V 25.</note> 
               <hi>I will turne my hand vpon thee, and purely purge away thy droſſe, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all thy tinne.</hi> The like promiſe is Iſa. 4.4. that he will <hi>waſh the filthineſſe of the daughter of Sion, by the ſpirit of iudgment, and by the ſpirit of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. both Preiſts and people all being ſo corrupt, that their caſe was deſperate, the Lord reſolues what to doe. <hi>I will goe and returne to my place,</hi> (that is, I will withdraw all the teſtimonies of my loue &amp; fauour from them) <hi>till they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their offence, and ſeeke my face:
<note place="margin">V. 15.</note> in their afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they will ſeeke me earlie.</hi> Which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly verified in the euent; for in the next words, the Prophet bringeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſpeaking thus in their affliction. <hi>Come let vs returne vnto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> and finally, the Lord promiſing to incline his Church, namely to obedience, he ſheweth by what meanes he will doe it, euen by bringing her into the wildernes. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Behold I will incline her,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8949:13"/>and bring her into the wilderneſſe;</hi> or after that I haue brought her into the wildernes: by the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is meant extreame miſerie: the reby ſhewing that the Iewes could not be inclined to obedience, vntill they were preſſed with diuers calamities, as it were caſt into a deſert of deſperation. So that the Lord dealeth with vs, as the Smith with the iron. Iron is very hard, but the Smith knoweth how to mollifie it, and make it flexible by putting it into the fire; ſo our hearts are ſo hard, that when God would make them flexible vnto his obedience, he is faine to caſt them into the fierie furnace of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby they are mollified. Yet many hearts are ſo hard, that the fire it ſelfe will not ſoften them, nor God's judgements moue them. So the Lord complaineth of his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.13, <hi>The people tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to him that ſmiteth them.</hi> And <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.7. <hi>the Storke in the heauen knoweth her appointed times, &amp;c. but my people know not the iudgments of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 4.</note> And by the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> he reckoneth vp his ſeuerall judgements wherewith he had afflicted them, as famine, peſtilence, the ſword: and after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them is ſubjoyned; <hi>yet haue ye not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned vnto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This contempt of God's judgments hath three degrees. 1. carnall ſecuritie, when a man is not moued with God's judgments before they ſeaze v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him: but although they be threatned againſt him, and he ſee them already vpon others, and he find in himſelfe the cauſe that will procure them; yea &amp; he perceiue God's inſtruments ſet on worke
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8949:13"/>to effect them: yet he bleſſeth himſelfe in his heart, and hauing made a couenant with death and with hell, he ſleepes as ſecure as <hi>Ionas</hi> did in the ſhip. Thus it was with the old World, <hi>they ate, dranke,
<note place="margin">Math. 24.38.</note> married wiues, and knew nothing,</hi> (that is, feared nothing) <hi>till the flood came and tooke them all away.</hi> Thus it fared with <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> he was feaſting with his Princes, his wiues, and his concubines, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſing out of the holy veſſels, at the ſame time when the hand-writing on the wall denounced his deſtruction: ſo the whore of <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> euen then when her fall is begunne, <hi>ſaith in her heart. I ſit a Queen,
<note place="margin">Revel. 18.7.</note> and am no widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow.</hi> But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſee an example of this ſecuritie in the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12. <hi>In that day did the Lord of hoſts call to weeping and mourning, to baldneſſe, and girding with ſackcloath, and behold ioy and gladnes; &amp;c.</hi> If this ſhould be found to be our caſe, we haue great cauſe for to feare; for the Scripture hath alwayes marked this ſecuritie, as a certaine fore-runner of deſtruction, and experience hath taught vs, that <hi>quos perdere vult <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upiter, hos occaecat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 2 degree is ſenſeleſſe indolencie, and bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh ſtupiditie, when a man is not affected with greife, euen then when Gods hand lieth heauy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, but puts off the feeling thereof with deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate contempt, labouring to outface his greifes, and forget his ſoares, by goeing into merry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, gaming, feaſting, reuelling, and ſuch other carnall delights: who may be compared to Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons drunkard, who ſleepes ſecurelie in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8949:14"/>of the ſea, and on the top of the maſt, whom he bringeth in ſpeaking thus,
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>they haue ſtricken me and I was not ſicke, they haue beaten me and I felt not.</hi> Amongſt the Heathens we haue many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples hereof. <hi>Ariſtides</hi> was not moued with his baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, nor <hi>Regulus</hi> with his exquiſit torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, nor <hi>Scipio</hi> with all thoſe indignities which his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull countrimen offered vnto him: nor <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> and <hi>Horatius Puluillus</hi> with the death of their children. This was commended by the Stoicks for great patience: but indeed as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>nulla virtus eſt quae non ſentias perpeti:</hi> there can be no patience, where there is no paſſion. And here there is no feeling; for this indolencie is a kind of dead palſie, or ſleepie lethargie, and (<hi>as S. Auſtine</hi> ſaith) it is <hi>ſtupor morbi,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De patient. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 23.</note> non robur ſanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> The Iſraelites are taxed with this Ier. 5.3. <hi>Thou haſt ſtricken them, but they haue not ſorrwed, thou haſt conſumed them, but they haue refuſed to receaue correction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt degree is when a man is moued with Gods iudgements, but not effectually. Thus there are many, who being afflicted, mourne too much, complaine, crie, houle, and wring their hands: and yet the ſenſe of judgement neuer driues them vnto true repentance. But either their ſorrow is onely naturall for the affliction; they ſay with Pharaoh, <hi>Take away the plague,</hi> not with Dauid, <hi>take away the ſinne:</hi> or els they are ſo farre from any humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation for their ſinnes, that they are rather moued to thinke that God muſt needs loue them, becauſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8949:14"/>he corrects them: Or finally, if the ſenſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, bring them to the ſight of their ſinnes; yet there followeth no amendment, but they are ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp of deſpaire; and hauing a ſight of their ſinnes in the glaſſe of the Law, without any ſenſe of Gods mercie revealed in the Goſpell, their hearts are broken and battered, but not diſſolued and ſoftened.
<note place="margin">Prov. 27.22.</note> So that <hi>though thou ſhouldeſt bray a foole in a morter, yet will not his fooliſhneſſe depart from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue I diſcouered this monſter with many heads. You ſee, that a dry ſoule that is void of grace, is a hard heart; a ſtiffe and vnyeelding will, is a hard heart: a dead and dull mind, that is not moued with Gods word is a hard heart: a ſeared conſcience that neuer ſmiteth for ſinne, is a hard heart: and finally blockiſh affections, that are not ſenſible of Gods iudgements, are a hard heart. Oh now that we would enter application vpon our owne ſoules, and examine what want of grace is in the ſoule, what rebellion in the will, what op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt Gods word in the mind, what <hi>Numneſſe</hi> and <hi>dumneſſe</hi> in the conſcience. And finally what contempt of Gods iudgements in the affections. And I doubt, that vpon this ſearch it will be found, that this hardnes of heart is an epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicall diſeaſe, that poſſeſſeth the whole body of the land.</p>
            <p>Now if we be ſicke of this diſeaſe, it is meete that in the next place, we ſhould proceed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the cauſe of this euill. And vpon triall,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8949:15"/>it will be found to be within vs: for my Text aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes it to our ſelues; <hi>harden not your hearts.</hi> Which is to be vnderſtood of voluntarie or habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hardnes: for there is a naturall hardneſſe which we ſucke from the tender breaſts of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all men being borne, as with a darke mind, ſo with a hard heart. And there is a iudiciarie hardneſſe, which God as a iuſt iudge inflicteth as a judgement vpon ſome notorious offenders,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1 27. Revel. 22.11. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>a recompence of their former errours as is meet,</hi> that <hi>they who are filthy may be more filthy, Iudicio vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, ſuo aliquando aperto, aliquando occulto, ſemper aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> juſto.</hi> Thus God in Scripture is ſaid, <hi>Percutere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia &amp; ſcotomate,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 19.14. Iſa. 29.10. Iſa. 6.10.</note> to ſtrike men</hi> with <hi>maddeneſſe</hi> and <hi>blindneſſe; to mingle among them the ſpirit of errour,</hi> and <hi>the ſpirit of ſlumber; to blind their eyes, make their eares heauy</hi> and <hi>their hearts fat:
<note place="margin">Math. 6.13. Rom, 1.24.26.28.</note> to leade men into temptation; to giue them ouer to vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to vile affections,</hi> to <hi>a reprobate mind;</hi> to <hi>ſend ſtrong deluſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.11.</note> or <hi>the efficacie of errours.</hi> And oftentimes he is ſaid to <hi>harden the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here there is great queſtion, after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner God hardens the heart, whether onely priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, as <hi>deſerendo,</hi> forſaking them, and <hi>permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo,</hi> not hindering them, and <hi>non puniendo;</hi> or <hi>per Patientiam,</hi> and <hi>dilatione poenae,</hi> in not puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing them. Or if he concurre to the hardening of the hearts alſo actiuelie, and that either by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward objects and occaſions, or by themſelues, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them ouer to their owne hearts luſts, or by Satan, to whoſe power he deliuereth ſuch hearts,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8949:15"/>for him to worke vpon, as a judge deliuereth the malefactor to the hang-man to be tormented: Or finally inwardly ſo working by his inuiſible power, that their corrupt hearts are more and more har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened. Indeed I dare not aduenture to wade into this depth. Onely this I muſt ſay, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's words doe manifeſtly ſignifie an action, and cannot without wreſting bee drawen vnto a bare permiſſion. Beſides it is as injurious to the diuine majeſtie, to robbe him of his power, wiſdome, and prouidence; as to accuſe his juſtice. And Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus his blaſphemie is not more carefully to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided on the one ſide, then the Pelagian Hereſie is on the other Therfore we muſt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider God as an idle beholder of wicked actions, like the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et's Iupiter, who was feaſting in Aethiopia, while things went out of order: but as an omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Creator giuing power and life to all, and by his concurrence cauſing euery motion and action in the creature: Alſo as a moſt wiſe gouernour, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering euen that which he made not: And finally as a iuſt judge, puniſhing ſinne by ſinne. Further let vs conſider that euen thoſe ſinnes, which are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnes, and not alſo puniſhments, are done by Gods permiſſion. Permiſſion hath place in all ſins, euen in the ſinnes of the godlie, yea in the firſt ſinne that euer was, <hi>quia non fieret ſi non ſineret.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Enchir, c.</hi> 100.</note> ſaith Auſt. And ſhall we thinke that God hath no further hand in this judiciarie obduration of wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men? Surely, then God might as well be ſaid to ſteale, murther, commit adultery, as to harden
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8949:16"/>the heart, becauſe he permitteth theſe ſinnes to be done: Then, why ſhould it onely be ſaid of noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wicked perſons, and not of all, that God har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth them? Finally, then ſhall not obduration be a puniſhment, as is acknowledged by all, euen by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De ſtat. pecc. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> For puniſhments are juſt and from God, as they are puniſhments, though they be alſo ſinnes. As ſaith the Maſter of the Sentences, <hi>ea quae peccata ſunt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 36. <hi>&amp; diſt.</hi> 32.</note> &amp; poena peccati</hi> &amp;c. That which <hi>is both a ſinne,</hi> and <hi>a puniſhment of ſinne, is of God, as it is a puniſhment; for all puniſhments are juſt.</hi> He giueth inſtance of concupiſcence, <hi>Concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia in quantum poena peccati, Deum habet autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> And <hi>Ferus</hi> applieth it to this point we haue in hand, ſaying that hardneſſe of heart is of God as it is <hi>Poena,</hi> not as it is <hi>Culpa.</hi> And laſt of all, if we reſpect the conſent of the fathers, ſurely S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> was reſolute in this point, that God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth in the hardening of the heart, <hi>Non mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſecundum permiſſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">l. 5. <hi>cont. Iulian</hi>
                  </note> vel patientiam, ſed etiam ſecundum actionem &amp; potentiam.</hi> To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe could I alleage many ſentences of the Ieſuites and beſt learned School-men: yet ſuch is their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that they accuſe that for hereſie and blaſphemie in vs, which is approued for Catholique doctrine, when it paſſeth from their quill. I will not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe theſe foule-mouthed Rabſakeh's, ſent forth to raile on the hoſt of the liuing God, any other anſwere, then what Michael the Arch-angell gaue vnto their father. The <hi>Lord rebuke</hi> thee, <hi>Satan.</hi> Onely giue me leaue, to vindicate Gods Iuſtice.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8949:16"/>
            <p>This that hath been ſaid of Gods hardening ſeemes vnto carnall minded men, who meaſure all things by the crooked rule of their owne reaſon, to caſt ſome aſperſion vpon God: Therefore will I breifely ſhew that God cannot be accuſed, for hardening the heart. The firſt reaſon is, becauſe God doeth not make any heart that is ſoft to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hard; but onely, that heart which already is hard, partly by nature, and partly by cuſtome, he hardens yet more, ſealing it vp, as it were,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.35.</note> vnto eternall condemnation. 2. Becauſe God is deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to no man, ſo that he is not bound to giue his grace vnto any man, or to hinder him from ſinne or to abſtaine from doing of theſe things, which are good in themſelues, though man be readie to abuſe them vnto euill. A third Reaſon I will bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from iudicious S. Auſtin, teaching vs, that God concurreth in hardening of the heart,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 5. <hi>cont. Iulian</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> actione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; potentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non ſane per qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiat, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatè durities ipſius cordis, ſed per quam multa fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant à quibus peccator vitio ſuo concipiat duritiem cordis.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, God doth not inſtill hardneſſe into any, nor produce it immediatly, nor enforce it as a neceſſarie effect: onely God doeth ſuch things, whence the ſinner through his owne fault, conceiueth hardneſſe. 4. It muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be remenbred that God hardens the heart <hi>Per judicium,</hi> for a puniſhment of their former ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe men receiue not the loue of the truth, God ſendeth them ſtrong deluſions.</hi> And ſo the Gentiles for their idolatrie, were <hi>ginen vp by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8949:17"/>God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> to their luſts, to vile affections, to a reprobate mind.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Nat. &amp; Grat. c.</hi> 12.</note> Which was <hi>a recompence of their errours at was meete.</hi> To this purpoſe ſaith Auſtin, <hi>priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meritis &amp;c. Hoc redditum eſt Pharaoni vt cor eius induraretur.</hi> The laſt conſideration I will vſe to iuſtifie God, is, that all iudiciarie obduration is alſo voluntary: So that no man is hardened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will; but they willingly draw vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the infliction of this iudgement, and freely ruſh into this pit of hardneſſe. Hence it is that as God is ſaid to harden <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his heart, ſo Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh is ſaid to harden his owne heart; and ſometimes it is ſimply ſaid that his heart was hardened, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the miniſtry of Satan. <hi>Deus indurauit per juſtum judicium,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Arb. c.</hi> 23.</note> Pharao per liberum arbitrium.</hi> The ſame hardneſſe is aſcribed to God as the judge, to Satan as the hangman, to man himſelfe as the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty guiltie. So likewiſe where the Apoſtle ſaith, that God <hi>gaue vp the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tile to vncleannes.</hi> Rom. 1.24. The ſame Apoſtle to ſhew that they were not giuen vp againſt their will: ſaith in another place, that they <hi>gaue vp themſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And therefore ſince men are willingly obſtinate and hard-harted, and willingly yeeld themſelues to their luſts, as thoſe who will not fight with their enemies, render themſelues willingly captiue to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them in euery thing: There is no reaſon why they ſhould accuſe any other then themſelues, as Auſtine ſweetlie, <hi>Ligatus teneor non ferro alieno, ſed mea ferrea voluntate,</hi> Neither neede we labour ſo much to know how God hardeneth, as how
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8949:17"/>we our ſelues become hardened. <hi>Origen</hi> well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerth, that whereas ſometimes Pharaoh is ſaid to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den his owne heart, and ſometimes God is ſaid to harden it: The firſt kind of hardening is declared by the Apoſtle how it commeth, euen when men by their impenitencie abuſe the lenitie of God. Rom. 2.5. But the ſame Apoſtle making mention of the other har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening by the Lord, Rom. 9. He paſſeth it ouer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any declaration, and it may be thought to be one of thoſe high matters, which Paul heard being taken vp into Paradiſe, and is not to be vttered. So I, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of the Apoſtle, and iudgement of <hi>Origen,</hi> will leaue to enquire into the manner of Gods hardening; and come to ſhew how it is that men harden their owne hearts.</p>
            <p>Here the Apoſtle hath eaſed me of a labour, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this in a word. ver. 13. that we <hi>are hardened through the deceitfulnes of ſinne,</hi> ſo it is ſaid of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh Exod. 9.34. <hi>Auxit peccatum, he ſinned yet more, and hardned his heart.</hi> The former is the cauſe of the latter. As a path is hardened by the continuall trampling of paſſengers, ſo is the heart by the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall cuſtome of ſinne. By our frequent ſinning, the ſoule is made dry; for euery ſinne is as fewell to the fire of concupiſcence, whereby the ſoule is burnt and dried vp. It is alſo by often ſinning that the will of it ſelfe rebellious, becommeth more inflexible; for the more a tree is backe-bended, the worſe it is to bow the right way: But euery ſinne is a back-be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of our will from God. Finally, by a cuſtomable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the mind is made ſo dull, that the word cannot pierce it; the affections ſo blockiſh, that Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8949:18"/>are not ſenſible vnto theur; and eſpecially the conſcience by this cuſtome of ſinne, groweth paſt all feeling.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tuſcul.</hi> 2.</note> For, as Tully ſaith, <hi>Labor callum quoddam obducit dolori.</hi> As Mithridates accuſtomed his body ſo much to the receit of poyſon, that at length no poyſon would worke on him: So he that accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his ſoule to the poyſon of ſinne, ſhall at length come to that paſſ,e that he will feele no ſin: For, ſaith Auſtin,
<note place="margin">Serm. 4. in Adven.</note> 
               <hi>omne peccatum vileſcit conſuetudine &amp; ſit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini quaſi nullum.</hi> The cuſtome of ſinne takes away the ſenſe of ſin.
<note place="margin">Rom. 2 15.</note> At firſt the light of Nature ſtands out againſt ſin, &amp; (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>our thoughts accuſe vs.</hi> But when we are often carried to commit ſinnes againſt the light of Nature, by practiſe of ſuch ſinnes the light of Nature is extinguiſhed:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſ de lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. L.</hi> 3.</note> for <hi>Iuſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima poena eſt, vt qui ſciens rectum non facit, amittat ſcire quod rectum,</hi> &amp; then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the reprobat mind, which judgeth euill, good; &amp; good, euill: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> followeth the ſeared co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. At the firſt a mans conſcience ſpeakes vnto him; as <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Chriſt, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, pittie thy ſelfe.</hi> Her prick-arrowes as the ſhafts of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> forewarne <hi>Dauid</hi> of the great Kings diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: but if we neglect her call, and will not lend our cares, while ſhe doth ſpend her tongue, this good <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandra</hi> wil cry no more, &amp; ſo we become paſt feeling. As the eye of al other parts of the body is moſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, &amp; impatient of the lighteſt touch; but if it be couered with a hard fleſhlie skin, called <hi>Scirrhoſis oculi,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth of all other parts moſt inſenſible. So the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience at firſt is ſo tender, that ſmall ſinnes vexe and torment it, but when through cuſtome of ſinning it is ouer-ſpread with a <hi>Callum,</hi> or thick skin, it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8949:18"/>inſenſible, &amp; nothing will wound it. This is not done in an inſtant, but piece &amp; piece, by degrees; firſt ſin is importable, then heavy, after that light, &amp; laſtly paſt feeling. At the firſt ſinne is importable, it ſeemes intollerable to be borne, it made <hi>Dauid</hi> cry out,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 33.4.</note> 
               <hi>Day &amp; night thy hand was heauy vpon me.</hi> &amp; againe, <hi>there is no reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſin:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 38 3.</note> for mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are gone ouer my head, as an heavy burden they are too heauy for me.</hi> But it is not long ſo: for ſin being commited twice or thriſe, is not as before im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, only it is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ewhat heauy. we are ſorry for it, but not ſo caſt down with it, as in former times. After this, ſin being often committed, that which at firſt was importable, &amp; afterwards heauy, becommeth light &amp; eaſie, it neuer breaks our ſleepe. &amp; then in the laſt place after that ſin is made light of, and that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe for ſin, then men grow paſt feeling, in a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe, giuen ouer to worke vncleannes euen with greedines, as hauing carouſed the cup of ſlumber vnto the very dregs. Here is <hi>deſcenſus Averni,</hi> theſe are the ſtaires that lead vnto the chambers of death, and the ſteps whereby the wicked doe deſcend into this pit of obduration.</p>
            <p>But, as S: <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith in another caſe, if the towne be on fire, we ſhould not be ſo curious to know how it came in, as carefull to put it out: Therefore in the laſt place, let vs bethinke our ſelues of a ſalue for this ſoare. Indeed it is a moſt dangerous &amp; deſperate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. The ſtone in the heart is a great deale worſe than the ſtone in the bladder; for after hardnes commeth <hi>the heart that cannot repent, Rom.</hi> 2.5. and without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance there can be no ſaluation. So that <hi>he who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8949:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>hardeneth his heart ſhill fall into euill Prov.</hi> 28.14.
<note place="margin">Eccles. 3.27.</note> and as the Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>man ſaith, <hi>Cor durum habebit malè in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſsimo.</hi> It ſhalbe in an ill caſe at the laſt day. Therfore you ſee that as when God would ſhew mercy to a people, he hath no more forcible meanes to expreſſe the ſame, then to ſay, <hi>I will take away the ſtonie heart:</hi> ſo when he would take vengeance on any, he hath no more grieuous way to doe it, then by hardening of their hearts, or giuing them vp to the hardnes of their hearts. It is no maruell then that the Scripture doth ſo carefully dehort vs from this hardnes of heart. and on the other part doth ſo earneſtly recommend vnto vs the contrary to a hard heart,
<note place="margin">Deut 10.16. Luc. 6.15. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 51.17. Iſa. 66.2. 2. King. 22.19. Ezech. 36.26.</note> which is ſet forth in Scripture by ſundry properties; as that it is <hi>a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed contrite heart, a good and honeſt heart, a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and contrite heart, a relenting; melting, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling heart, a poore, humble and obedient heart, a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart, a new heart, ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, waſhed by his grace, heated &amp; inflamed by his holy ſpirit.</hi> In a word, <hi>a heart of fleſh,</hi> or a ſoft heart, that is ſoone checked &amp; controlled, ſoone pierced, ſoone made to bleed; ſoon ſtirred vp to amendment.</p>
            <p>Now that we may get ſuch a heart, theſe remedies are to be vſed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which will be like a pretious balme to ſoften and ſupple our hearts. 1. We muſt beware of frequent ſinning, and learne to make conſcience of euery ſinne,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſince cuſtomable ſinning is that which hardens the heart. In the next place, let vs labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter true ill mination; for the hardneſſe of our heart is from the blindnes of our mind: vnleſſe the mind be firſt inlightened,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> the heart can neuer be ſoftened. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this we muſt lay our hearts open and naked to all admonitions, threatnings, exhortations of the word,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8949:19"/>applying them to our owne conſcience; for that is <hi>the hammer that breaketh the ſtones,</hi> it is <hi>the fire that mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the hardeſt mettals:</hi> it is <hi>the two edged ſword, that pierceth to the diuiding aſunder of the ſoule and ſpirit.</hi> This <hi>Recipe</hi> is preſcribed by the Apoſtle, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after, <hi>exhort one another daily, while it is called to day,
<note place="margin">v. 13.</note> leſt any of you be hardened through the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourchly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> we muſt often enter into a conſideration of our own eſtates; for we periſh for want of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, becauſe we mind not what we doe, or in what caſe we ſtand to Godward. <hi>No man repented,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi> but why? <hi>No man ſaid, what haue I done, but as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> horſe ruſheth into the battaile, ſo they into their ſinnes.</hi> Therefore it behooueth vs to examine our wayes, &amp; to erectan inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; keep an <hi>audit</hi> in our hearts, looking vpon our ſelues continually in the glaſſe of the Law; and therein meditating often vpon the Iuſtice of God, &amp; his greathatred againſt ſin, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth of God's threatnings, vpon the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the fearefull torments prepared in hell for hard-hearted ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. And if thou thus ſtrike the rock of thy heart with the rod of the Law, riuers of Water will guſh forth. 5. But leſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> after that in the Law we haue ſeen our miſerable &amp; deſperate eſtate, we ſhould preſently raue &amp; rage againſt the Lord; we muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r with the ſight of our ſinnes, to get a ſight of Gods mercie reuealed in the Goſpell. The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his fathers houſe, made the heart of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall to relent: ſo will the conſideration of Gods mercies towards vs, worke vpon our hearts: when once our hearts are inflamed with the ſenſe of Gods loue towards vs, oh then the working of our bowels!
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8949:20"/>the ſtirring of our affections! the melting and relen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our repenting hearts.</p>
            <p>Sixtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> let vs obſerue duelie the judgements of God; for all afflictions whether vpon our ſelues, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, ſhould ſtirre vs vp, and make vs looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs. The famine, the ſword, the peſtilence, are Gods three Champions to fight his battails, &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his quarrels, but eſpecially the Peſtilence, that is called <hi>Bellum Dei contra homines.</hi> Theſe three ſhould be vnto vs as the three arrowes which <hi>Iona. than</hi> ſhot to forewarne <hi>Dauid</hi> of the Kings diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: As <hi>Dauid</hi> vnderſtood thereby that the King was angry, and ſo got vp, and made haſt to be gone: So may we by thoſe darts that come from Heauen, &amp; fall ſo neere vnto this place, perceiue that the wrath of God is kindled againſt vs: And therefore we ſhall doe well, to get vp, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, and make haſt to flee from the face of an angry God, whoſe wrath is a conſuming fire, hiding our ſelues in the holes of that rocke Chriſt Ieſus, who is a propitiation for our ſins. But this is not all to perceiue by Gods judgements that he is angry. In the next place, we ſhall doe well to looke backe into our ſelues, and enquire what we haue done, that hath prouoked the Lord to wrath; for he neuer ſtrikes without a cauſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. 21.1.</note> So <hi>Dauid</hi> when the famine was vpon the land, conſulted with the Lord, and he found, that it was for the bloud of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſhed by <hi>Saul.</hi> Yea ſo much deuotion we may learne from the <hi>Aſſyrians.</hi> After the king of <hi>Aſhur</hi> had ſent into <hi>Samaria</hi> new Colonies from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, Cutha, Ana, Hamath,</hi> and from <hi>Sepharuaim,</hi> there came Lions and deſtroyed them. And they rightly apprehended the cauſe of it to be; for that they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8949:20"/>did not worſhip the God of the land; but ſerued i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols in that place, which the Lord of hoſts had ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified for his owne worſhip: Wherevpon the king gaue order, that one of the Preiſts ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried backe,
<note place="margin">2. King. 17.24. &amp;c.</note> to teach them the manner of the God of the land. Belike they knew that the Arke of God &amp; Dagon wold not dwel vnderone roof. So if we ſearch into the cauſe that hath prouoked God to wrath, we will finde ſuch as this, and many more in ourſelues. So the conſideration of Gods judgements will bring vs to the ſight of our ſinnes, which is a good meanes to make our hearts relent.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> let vs bath our hearts in the hot bloud of Ieſus; for the conſideration of his death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is a moſt effectuall meanes to make our hearts relent and reſolue into the teares of vnfained contrition: for did Chriſt for our ſinnes ſhed his heart bloud? &amp; did our ſinnes make him ſweat water &amp; bloud? &amp; ſhould not we ourſelues ſhed bitter teares, ſhould not our hearts bleed for them? Did the vaile of the Temple rend, and the ſtones cleaue aſunder, when Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered? &amp; ſhall not our ſtonie hearts breake, for whom he ſuffered? Did the earth moue, and ſhall our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minds ſtand immoueable? No, no, if we could be ſetled in this without doubt, that we were the men that crucified Chriſt, as guilty of his death, as was <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, Iudas,</hi> or the <hi>Iewes;</hi> that our ſinnes were the nailes that boared his hands and his ſeete, and the ſpeare which pierced his ſide, and the thornes that pricked his head. If, I ſay, this meditation could take place in our hearts; bitternes of ſpirit, with wailing and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhould take place in like manner. Thus, <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſermon. Act. 2. ſtrooke the Iewes as with a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derclap
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8949:21"/>from Heauen, when he told them, that they had crucified the Lord of glory, ſo that 3000 of them were pricked in their hearts,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> and cried, <hi>Men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, what ſhall we doe?</hi> Euen ſo if we be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe vpon whom God hath promiſed to powre forth his ſpirit in the laſt dayes; <hi>We ſhall looke vpon him whom we haue pierced, and we ſhall lament for him, as one mourneth for his onely ſon.</hi> Zach. 12.10. Finally, becauſe a ſoft heart is the gift of God; let vs haue recourſe vnto him by earneſt and freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayer, beſeeching him of his fatherly goodnes, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his promiſes in the new couenant, he would take away this ſtonie heart from vs, and giue vs a heart of fleſh, which may receiue the ſtampe of his word, be pliable to the operation of his bleſſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and tremble at his iudgements. And vnto prayer we muſt ſometimes adde faſting, which is like ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, now &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be joyned with ordinary waſhing. When deſtruction was threatened againſt <hi>Niniveh</hi> the King proclaimed a ſolemne faſt; ſo hath our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious King done at this time: Not as the king of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh.</hi> For that king did proclaime the faſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vpon the warning of a Prophet: but he himſelfe gaue warning to the Prophets, and like the good Kings of <hi>Iuda,</hi> we haue ſeene him goe before the Prieſts, in the zeale of Gods ſeruice. I will not foreſtall the market, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the worke of the day, for the day it ſelfe. Onely giue me leaue to blow the trumpet in <hi>Sion</hi> for ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of this faſt, and to ring a peale this day before, giuing you warning that if ye will heare his voice, &amp; meete the Lord by repentance in that day of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; <hi>yee muſt not harden your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
